e
[Music]
Carol
mandle for
[Music]
we have very interesting guest here can
you please introduce yourself for our
listeners so my name is Professor Carol
andell I'm director of science at the
European space agency and also head of
the European space Astronomy Center
outside Madrid V so we are little busy
as you can hear right now because we are
the staros festival and we are just
trying to find interesting guests to
well ask difficult question my first
difficult question for you is why do we
wait so long for the Lisa Mission so the
Lisa mission is outstanding iconic
technology that we have to invent um we
had a mission called the Lisa Pathfinder
Mission and this was really the mission
that let us test out some of our ideas
one of the things we had to do was make
sure that we could fly a spacecraft that
has a test mess on it and the test Mass
should not know it's on a spacecraft
because it has to feel gravity in the
universe without actually knowing it's
being flow on a spacecraft so we
actually have to develop really
pioneering Technologies for Rossy it
does sound impossible doesn't it but
Lisa Pathfinder showed us that it was
possible and in fact actually the data
that we got back to Leisa Pathfinder
were already at the design sensitivity
before the scientists did any extra
calibration so we already know we can do
this and what we have to do for the
lease submission in full is design three
identical IC spacecraft and they will
each point at one another they will make
an equilateral triangle with separation
of 2 and A2 million kilometers between
each of the space Crow and then it will
fly as a rigid triangle along an orbit
behind or in front of the earth one
astronomical unit away from the Sun and
so that mission we have lots of
technology to develop we've done the
studies we know with think we know how
to do this and this year our governing
body of 22 me the states who pay money
into Issa for the science program agreed
with us that the technology is now ready
to be developed and so we will now put
our contract call out to Industry and
there'll be a competition uh across
European industry for a prime company to
Wi to develop this Mission with other
companies that CR so it's after RMA
stage and you're moving into the
manufacturer stage exact oh good luck
with those it's an iconic timer I was
very excited it was a very exciting
interesting and T Wednesday when we
actually asked our 22 member states to
come to Paris and adopt not only the
Leisa ad Mission but also the Envision
Mission which is our mission that will
go to Venus so adoption means that they
say yes we approve you should go ahead
now uh design the contracts put them out
to Industry and go ahead and build the
missions so 22 countries voted
unanimously to support the development
of both of these missions and what
should it reveal well it will will
reveal the nature of space I can't
overstate it um it's we've never flown
as a species an interferometer for
gravitational waves in space before it
will probe a kind of space-time Ripple
that we're not able to do from the earth
so at the moment we have gravitational
wave detectors on ground and they've
been iconic in helping us prove that
gravitational radiation can be detected
and resulted in Nobel prizes um but it
was stellam mass black holes and neutron
stars that colled to produce the kind of
ripples at the frequency we can detect
on Earth if we want to look at much more
massive black consum super massive black
holes Collide or the ripples in space
time that are the remnants of the Big
Bang we have to go to these very long
Baseline lens which means we have to go
to space which is what Lisa will do so
is the next from the
gravitational W call for Earth it is
it's the next Frontier and it's the
first time ever we will appr prob space
time on these scales and these energies
because these are the most violent
processes in the universe what we will
do is we will use Galactic binaries as
the calibration the cosmic calibration
for the spacecraft to prove that we are
really probing gravitational ways it
will take us about a year to build up
that knowledge to be really testing the
data that come from the the mission and
speaking of violent outbursts we are
also involved in Garay burst right I am
that's my one of my areas of research
interest obviously now as director of
science at Issa I've put all of my
research to one side because I have to
be fair to all of my portfolios from the
sudden and outwards um but yeah my my
background is in study black Co super
master of black holes to begin with and
then I moved into time domain astronomy
and studying Gamay bursts in real time
so real time autonomous systems magnetic
fields what fuels these incredible
explosions and what they can ultimately
tell us about the universe it's
interesting because I study Quantum
space and it's related to both black HS
and gar reverse there was the detection
of
grb
22 109 you know the the most energetic
one which basically violated the current
known laws of physics and one of the
possible explanation is that well space
itself has some Quantum structure and
slows down some of the wave of length
and moves the threshold a little bit and
the other thing is well small BL holes
should be evaporated by hu radiation but
if the space is some Quantum
structure then well basically it freezes
the process and maybe they can be
constituents of the dark matter but
before becoming the remnants they'll
just evaporate very rapidly M ver it is
very unfortunate we haven't seen this
before but when Des sending on new
assumtions is now quantum gravity
Quantum space and achievable role role
in mind well I think this is one of the
big unsolved frontiers of physics
obviously to combine the laws of physics
and the smallest scales govern by
quantum mechanics with the laws of of
physics and the largest scales govern by
govern by gravity I think one of the
challenges we have and I really push
this back to our theoretical physicist
and I know you're a theoretical physic
says I'm going to put this back on your
table I think out my homework you you
have to do your homework what you have
to give us is testable predictions so I
think there are something like 24 or 26
different models of quantum gravity none
of them are complete they all have
various different constraints and that's
understandable this is a really hard
problem to solve um some of them do
produce testable predictions so for
example the you know variable speed of
light Lance and variance violation and I
think we have some constraints on those
um I think we can go further one of the
things that I was interested as when in
my research was actually using and
gammaray bursts through Cosmic distance
and if we understand the intrinsic
properties of the magnetic fields we can
use a special property of the like
called polarization and actually how
does that polarization um reflect
potentially the quantum foam scale of of
the cosmos of SpaceTime but for me you
know I can design an experiment to do
that but I also need Theory colleagues
to come and say here is a definitive
prediction you know if you measure this
then it it really constrains the models
if you detect this it constrains and
models in a different way so I think we
really are at the frontiers of physics
and really progress comes step by step
so we'll have a testable prediction
we'll then go and design a mission and
in fact we did that in my research group
studying magnetic fields so obviously
gamma Ras the question was are they
flows of plasma or is that plasma
actually governed by large scale Lo of
magnetic fields and it was a very Cen
experiment I the light is highly
polarized in which case you have large
scale load of magnetic fields or it's
not polarized and you just have a
hydrogen elic flow what was challenging
was being able to get onto those Gamay
bursts in a very few minutes after the
explosion when the primordial magnetic
field if it exists is still encoded in
the light and that was what we did in my
group where we pioneered these this
noral little polar called Ringo and then
the success of Ringo 2 and Ringo 3 on
the world's largest autonomous robotic
telescope the Liverpool telescope the 2
m fully autonomous telescope and we
followed up in real time gam burst
detected by Swift and we made the
detection a 40% polarized light in the
first minutes after the grb and we could
also see how that polarized light
evolved though we proved that there are
large scale aut magnetic fields so that
for me was a very powerful use of the
scientific method clear distinctions
between the theories the brightness of
the light and how the light changes was
not a testable prediction because both
wles gave the same answer you had to go
look at the polarization of the light in
order to distinguish the MERS so I come
back to Quantum gravitative colleagues
and say come forward with some really
concrete testable predictions that we
can then go and invent the technology to
test but the tricky part is well we
expect that the scale of the quantum
gravity is the blank scale at maybe it's
or or below or above or something like
that and that is difficult to make
predictions but I think there are some
preliminary results with the vacuum
dispersion basically slowing down some
of the wavelengths and now uh mission is
being built hermas telescope that should
be able basically to detect and then say
we we need a big maybe not even a bigger
telescope maybe faster detection rate
because we need gr small differences
maybe larger detection area or something
like this so I think we are moving that
way guessing that yeah and there was an
interesting Mission uh designed in
Slovakia also Czech Republic Hungary I
think also Japan grb Alpha Now grb Beta
which is a nano satellite they all
basically one New Cube set which
detected Garay burst and when um I think
was F telescope one of the nas telescope
was well Overexposed by the data
colleting during the largest then the
small satell actually are good because
well they are not Overexposed during the
strong burst so maybe they will also
play a role and they are very fast they
can be built quickly cheaply so the bo
will call you yeah I think when you're
talking about getting to the plank scale
obviously you need to go to the highest
energies if you're going to go to second
order models um I think your first order
models you may do in the optical or
slightly higher frequencies I think one
of the challenges is doing this across
the electromagnetic spectrum because if
you just do this in the gamma rays
you're still model dependent because we
still don't understand enough about the
physics of the plasma flames and I think
one of the really big challenges of
doing that kind of fundamental physics
experiment at with a source that's you
know millions and millions of light
years away is actually understanding the
intrinsic Source physics the physics of
what's going on around the black ho in
the plasma with the magnetic to that's
already quite complicated and
disentangling with a propagation effects
through a quantum foam C distance but I
think you know we have to build up
larger samples we have to have new
future missions and my personal personal
preference it's just my personal
preference if I were still in research
would be to do a polarized Mission
across the entire electromagnetic
spectrum because then you can Pro the
synchroton physics the shock physics and
you can start to do that across large
wave of the sky at different Cosmic
distances maybe you can start then to
get some realistic constraints on the
cosmological properties of space t and I
think in the future will we have
missions like Lisa when we have missions
like new Athena and you know other
missions that might come from colies
like NASA and Jackson if we start to put
that whole time domain multimessenger
world together the role of B based
detectors with things like nutr when
we're starting to look at the same
sources across all of those tracers
hopefully we'll have enough information
in the bag to disentangle the different
types of physics that we'd like to PR so
we're here mul messenger
ask for sure yeah so misstion black we
didn't expect any black host couple of
decades ago May found the Stellar black
Hol super massive leg host probably soon
an intermediate Mass BL hole will be
announced as well but what about
microscopic BL holes we have any thought
like or is it like too hypothetical and
well it depends how micro me obviously
if they're really tiny they all they
will have evaporated already I think
it's very difficult to space might
perit I think it's quite tending to say
that little flash of light came from an
evaporating black hole and there's so
many other things that produce flashes
of light I mean obviously there are big
Grand based facilities like the large
synoptics survey telescope that you know
the the ruin Observatory um will start
to survey the transient sky and instead
of a few hundred transients per year we
expect to see Millions per night so I
think there'll be a whole trench of data
that we'll be able to mine into I think
you're right though in terms of the Mass
Spectrum were black holes we're now
starting to probe so many different
scales and I know our colleagues at ligo
Virgo kagra they keep a tally of all the
different massive black holes that we
now we now have so from the few solar
mass black holes up to the 30 solar mass
black holes that we detected with Gaia
and when you merge those together and
produce groundbased detected
gravitational WS that gives you the 60
solar mass black holes and then right up
to the super massive black hes and in
fact the web Space Telescope is showing
us that we produce or the universe can
can grow super massive black holes very
early on in the history of the universe
and we don't know how to do that there
shouldn't be enough Cosmic time to grow
10 to the N or 10 to the 10 s must if
they were formed by the traditional well
core collapsed process which which were
just some fluctuations very early in the
universe then it still maybe explain
okay I will take us from approach uh I
will ask you you are involved in NASA in
major
weight sorry uh what what are the ter
like three biggest missions in the
nearest Future you are very excited
about them can
you you're restricting me to
three let me tell you about the the
pathway that we have so obviously last
year we launch two iconic missions uh
one to go to Jupiter which is called
juice and this the idea of this Mission
it will go and it will look to test
whether the icy Winds of Jupiter are
actually habitable for life we think
that there are salty oceans below the
icy crust and we will actually test
whether they could be habitable for life
and one of the his is was wi in Slovakia
so we are very proud it's a fantastic
Mission there are 10 really brilliant uh
instruments and you know across all of
our member states and across you know
associate countries too continue I just
wanted to yeah no no I'm aware of that
and all the different components in
there so we're very excited about that
mission the other Mission uh is uclid
and this is really our dark Explorer to
study dark matter and dark energy in the
universe and how they're coupled so
those two missions for me are going to
really revolutionize our understanding
um of whole different parts of COS of
the cosmos really both in terms of
cosmology 95% of the universe that we
don't understand uid will unveil that to
us and the Other Extreme as whether um
our icym of Jupiter are actually
habitable and then every two years up
until 2037 the E of Science Program is
going to launch a major science Mission
so they have all of these missions in
preparation and are being prepared ready
for launch um we'll launch the swell
Mission with our Chinese colleagues
hopefully at the end of 2025 to really
study the interaction between the Sun
and the Earth's magnetosphere so that
will be really important let's study
that during solar Marx we've got two
really exciting exoplanet Mission so
Plato will launch hopefully in 2026 and
RN in 29 and we'll be able to look with
Plato at earthlike planets around
sunlike Stars so stut suddenly
understanding planets like our own
around other sunlike stars um Ariel will
then start to look at the atmospheres of
a thousand exoplanets so we'll actually
start to look at atmospheric chemistry
in the spal properties of a thousand
planets and start to compare that with
our earthlike environment which is kind
of incredible and you think you'll be
studying planetary atmospheres um you
CCI it does sound like Ci but it SCI
fact and we're actually designing that
mission and building it now across our
member states um and then as we go out
through 2031 35 37 obviously they'll
have en Vision which will go to Venus um
and will help us to study everything
from above the um the top of the ven
venutian atmosphere right down to the
core of the planet and help us to
understand why sister for it I mean
Venus should be like Earth but it's so
catastrophically different it's hot it's
really hostile we hope that Earth won't
evolve to become there but we'd like to
understand more about the papet and bis
uh does the wish w't land on the Venus
it won't land no but what it will do
because I found it in papers that it's
very difficult to land
there I have been probes in the past
that have done that but that's not what
we plan to do what we will do though is
we use the oy environment of Venus to to
slow our spacecraft down until it's in
orbit I think called era breaking which
is also technically quite hard to do and
then after that we will launch Lisa in
2035 uh that will take 2 years for the
mission to get to its operating uh
position in orbit around the Sun and
then in 20137 we hope to launch the next
big um world x-ray Observatory which is
called New Athena which will study the
hottest gas in the universe at a million
degrees so together we'll have this
incredible Fleet of of Ls that will do
everything that we want to understand
about our solar system how our planets
fit into the cosmic context of planets
around other stars and then ultimately
right out to the nature of SpaceTime all
the questions will be answered pleas
well I'm sure we'll
question you always open up new fronted
but of course we're already planning the
2040s and the 2050s so a few years ago
our scientific Community came together
um to think about what would be the big
questions we would want to to be asking
and answering because obviously it takes
some time to develop missions and we
need to start well
so we divis does you have to tell us the
questions you thinking well I mean you
know some of the big questions we want
to answer really I mean they still are
about life in the universe and the idea
is to build yeah exactly are we alone
that is quite existential and we want to
build on the technology that we've
already developed for juice and we said
to our scientists over the last couple
of years if we were to go somewhere in
the solar system and land and look for
life where we should where where should
we go and how should be go and there was
a 2-year scientific study and a 2-year
technical design study which we
published just this month and the answer
is out we're going to Enceladus which is
one of the moons of Saturn and they use
the the wonderful technology we
developed for juice to actually do fireb
of the wounds of Saturn and our
scientists said we'd like you to fly
through the plume what's huming out to
the salador but that's a lot of enough
we'll need you to land and we need you
to take some samples so we're going to
devise that that technology and
hopefully if our ministers come in 2025
and establish the right budgets for us
we'll have the money to start the
techology develop R is it like landing
on Europe and then drilling the whole a
plan or uh not Europa no so Europa is
one of the Jupiter moons um NASA will go
to Europa and go around it it's a very
hostile environment because it's very
the Moon is larger I think I think for
two agencies yeah well Europa is a very
hostile environment and we we will fly
by Europa and IA and kalista and ganam
and but the magnetic field properties
close to Jupiter where Europa is are
very very hostile so NASA's Europa
especially to own study Roper it won't
land but it will study that we will do a
flyby and then we will study the EV and
together the data will be combined and
give us a so we will be fly by in
Jupiter and they'll end be so so so our
big 2040s mission will actually go
straight to Saturn um and we'll do a fly
by of some of the moon so we've already
20 years ago we landed on Titan so we
know how to do that but we'll do a fly
by of the Saturn mes the big Saturn new
and then we will fly through the plume
of Enceladus and we will land on
Enceladus cuz we think Enceladus is the
best best Target for life in the out
solar Sy even better in Europe or Europe
is also good candidate but we have to
drill I I think better because the the
plumes suggest that there are fissures
and cracks in the surface and that the
material from the potentially the ocean
underneath is actually out so I that's
what our s yeah our scientists have told
they they did a whole different P of
study so there are S three key criteria
you need an energy source you need some
Li liid um and then you need to be able
to to access that and so they looked
they studied all of the moons and they
put all of these different criteria
together and the one that came through
that ticked all the boxes as and sold us
no okay okay uh you open your your door
with uh Landing One Titan are we
returning there at least is there a
fueling missioners that one met no we're
not returning to Titan cuz we've done
that already but NASA is hoping to
return to Titan very shortly with their
dragonfly Mission so this is a
development of their Martian helicopter
uh again a technology demonstrator so
that'll be really nice to see may find
on Titan we had a soft landing on Titan
because we assumed that there would be
liquid methane oceans and we thought
we'd better be able to float turned out
that it's all Frozen and so you see this
incredible Landing you can see you know
where those rivers and oceans have
flowed and we landed on that Frozen
River bed and it's a really beautiful
louy I mean the the land of lands it
looks you can see the the DW drop and
then you can see the sun in the distance
through the hydrocarbon Haze it's
absolutely is stunning to think we could
do that 20 years ago just shows what we
can do we be able to do in the 24 days
one Qui ask question what is our
estimate or finding light we demul lives
outside the world obviously I'm very
hopeful very hopeful in person 90% I
can't give a
percent well we found life on Earth
that's all I'm going to say okay thank
you very much you very much priv having
with us
Instagram
face
[Music]
V
Zo
[Music]